Boy, if you have blood pressure
problems, you're going to be pretty
happy you watched this video. I'm going
to talk about why people have
hypertension. The number one mineral
deficiency behind this whole thing. 90%
of all hypertension is essential
hypertension. What does that mean? It
means unknown cause, which is very
convenient for a drug company who sells
medications for blood pressure. I mean
in fact anti-hypertensive medication is
right at the top of the list as far as
most prescribed medications in the
world. First of all look what is
hypertension? What is blood pressure?
This top number which is systolic and
the bottom number which is diastolic.
Normally it should be 120 over 80. And
what this number represents is the
contraction of the heart muscle that
pushes the blood throughout the whole
body down to the little capillaries
where it then goes through veins and
eventually ends up into the lungs where
it gets reoxygenated. So the top number
is the contraction of the heart and the
bottom number is the relaxation of the
heart muscle. Collectively together this
systolic and diastolic is a heartbeat.
And when you have high blood pressure,
there's some type of a resistance going
on. It could be a blockage. It could be
a lot of things. But the point is that
when you have any type of blood pressure
issue, it puts more stress on the heart.
There's a lot of research in the
relationship between a potassium
deficiency. Personally, I think a
potassium deficiency is behind a good
majority of this essential hypertension.
Why do I say that? Well, number one,
most people are deficient in potassium.
Why are they deficient? Because it's a
bit hard to get potassium. Since the
requirements are so [snorts] high out of
all the nutrients, potassium is the
largest amount of nutrient that we need.
We need 4700
mg and an average person does not get
that much. And the other interesting
thing about medicine is that the whole
focus is to reduce sodium for
hypertension, right? But what about
enhancing potassium? They don't really
talk about that. What does lowering
sodium do? Well, it indirectly increases
potassium. We need about half the amount
of sodium to potassium. And I think
these ratios are more important than the
amounts. Many people are very heavy on
the sodium, very low in the potassium to
the point where they're like three times
as much sodium to potassium. But what
does potassium actually do to your blood
vessels in your heart? Number one, it
directly controls the tone of the
vascular system, which is the
neurotransmitter for the autonomic
nervous system, which is directly
connected to a high blood pressure
situation because when you're running up
a hill, you have adrenaline that kicks
in to raise the blood pressure. Well,
potassium lowers adrenaline. Potassium
helps support the layer of the inside of
the artery called the endothelial layer.
And potassium also helps improve insulin
resistance. It makes insulin more
sensitive. And what's wild is that when
you go buy a potassium supplement,
usually comes like no more than 99
milligs per tablet. How many tablets
would you have to take to achieve 4700?
Now there are electrolyte powders that
have more than that. The other
consideration that people have about
potassium is that, oh, potassium is bad
for the kidneys. That is completely
false. Potassium is very very healthy to
the kidney. It's protective of the
kidney. When you have advanced kidney
disease like a stage four, stage five,
that's when potassium can be dangerous.
Now, this next thing I'm going to tell
you is even more interesting because if
you look at the top medications for
blood pressure, they all retain
potassium. Interesting. Could it be that
some of the positive effects of these
blood pressure lowering medications
could be because of the potassium
effect? Now, where do we get our
potassium from? Well, you can get it
from salads, but you'd have to consume
at least 7 to 10 cups to make a dent
into this potassium requirement. And the
average person only consumes like a a
cup and a half. And also, these leafy
greens contain magnesium, too. So the
combination of both potassium and
magnesium will greatly help the blood
pressure. There's also data that in the
prehistoric uh paleolithic times there's
estimations that we consumed like 11,000
to 15,000
milligs of potassium. Now there's no way
to know this for sure. It's just a good
guess. But if you think about what we
used to eat way back in the day, we
pretty much ate whatever we could find.
If we could catch an animal, we would
eat it. If we couldn't catch an animal,
I'm sure that we would eat vegetation or
anything laying on the ground like an
acorn or anything. But when we consume
refined foods, especially refined sugar,
we lose potassium. When we increase
adrenaline or cortisol, we lose
potassium. So, I have a challenge for
you. I would recommend that you start to
beef up your potassium consumption
through salad. Just try it for one week
and see what happens to your blood
pressure. If you can't seem to manage
that much salad, then find a good
electrolyte powder high in potassium. I
think you might be pleasantly surprised
of all the amazing benefits. Now, just
to give you some visual on how much
salad you should consume, I put that in
this video right here. Check it out.
Hey, before you leave, I just wanted to
give you a little quick history on some
of the books that I wrote. This was one
of the first books. It's called Dr.
Burke Body Shapes. It was my attempt at
um writing about body types. Uh what was
very interesting about this book is I
actually did all the images myself. Uh
don't ask me why. Um they look actually
not quite as professional as some of the
uh images that I have in the new book.
But anyway, this is my first attempt
right here called Dr. B's body shaped
diets. Uh, and then I wrote a book, um,
more extensive called The Seven
Principles of Fat Burning. I don't even
have a copy anymore actually, um,
because it's outdated. Uh, the next
book, uh, I put about a thousand hours
into this one right here called The New
Body Type Guide. Major updates on the
body types. Uh, I put a lot of energy
into this. Uh, it has professional
images, graphics, all sorts of things.
Now, the problem with this book is it
doesn't really describe what this is
really about. Body types are only a
small portion of what's in this book.
And that's why I changed the name to the
healthy keto plan. Okay? If [snorts] you
happen to have this book, you don't
really need this book because there's
only very very minor updates. But if you
don't have this, you need to get this
one right here. Um, this book goes into
every single detail that you would ever
want to know about. It goes into the
seven principles of fat burning. Goes
into hormones, uh, the body types, the
basic keto plan, it goes into
intermittent fasting. I talk about the
10 fat burning triggers and blockers and
fat burning strategies with a lot of
details in every single chapter. I go
into body issues that interfere with
losing weight. Um there's very few
people that just have a weight problem.
They have a lot of body issues, whether
it's sleeping problems, uh stress
problems, inflammation,
menopause. I cover that extensively in
this book. Then I talk about how to get
rid of stress and I show you a
technique. Uh then I get into exercising
and then I have a lot of really good
recipes in this book as well. So, uh
this is a good reference guide. Um on my
website, if you get this book, you get
this one free. It's called Healthy Keto
and Intermittent Fasting. This is the
shortcut uh quick guide to this book.
And uh the reason I created this book is
to have you within 45 minutes learn how
to do keto, okay, in intermittent
fasting, exactly what you need to do.
Then you can fill in the blanks with
this book right here. So, right now I'm
doing a special. If you get this book,
you get this one totally free. Or you
can go to Amazon and get these
individually. So, I just want to clarify
the difference between this book and
this updated one right here. If you
don't have this, you need to get this
right here. That way, you can get the
exact correct information to do it
healthily.